python is a dynamically typed language
which means that with python you can do
crazy and silly things like this where
the name variable starts as a string and
then it becomes a number and finally
ends up as a Boolean that code might not
look so crazy to you but this python
feature that JavaScript shares as well
is the root of many runtime errors which
are errors that happen when the software
is running on the user's device
dynamically typed languages like
JavaScript or python are very beginner
friendly because they don't force the
developer to explicitly tell the program
the type of data it holds statically
typed languages like C C plus plus Java
C sharp typescript and go among many
others don't allow that in this c-sharp
code when I create a variable I first
have to indicate what type of data that
variable will hold because of this if I
later try to change the value of name to
a number I will get an error because the
language knows that name should be a
string and by trying to change it to a
number I might be making a mistake and
it is a mistake because changing the
type of a variable by accident can cause
other code that uses that variable to
fail take this python code for example
we have a function that takes a b and c
and Returns the result of a plus b plus
C we humans know that we should only
call this function with numbers but
python does not know that python does
not know what the type of a or b or c
should be and because of this it will
allow anything to go through so if
someone makes a tiny mistake and does
something like this sending the number 2
inside of a string python will still try
to run that code ending on an error
telling us that we cannot use the plus
sign between an integer and a string
statically typed languages like the ones
we mentioned before would not even allow
that code to run python of course is not
as strict and no one wants it to be but
wouldn't it be cool if we could get at
least a hint or a warning when we are
doing something dumb with types the good
news is that we can from python version
3.5 we can add type hints to our code
indicating what the types of things are
so next time you create a variable you
can add a type hint to it by using a
column and the python type so if we take
the code from the beginning and add type
hints we can then use a type Checker
like my pie to tell us where the
problems are my pie is a type Checker
that you can run in your console after
installing it doing fit insta though my
pipe or if you are using vs code and you
don't want to constantly have to be
running commands next time you are on a
python file go to the Bottom bar of your
vs code and switch type checking to on
when you do this vs code will warn you
after it checks your code using type
hints we can also fix the function we
created before to only accept integers
and we can even specify what is the type
the function returns so if we make a
mistake and send the wrong number of
argument or the wrong type our type
Checker can let us know when creating
arrays you can use type hints as well to
restrict them to one data type you can
also type dictionaries and using the
type in module you can express more
complicated types as well for example a
function that takes an optional string
parameter or a list that can have both
numbers and strings or when you don't
want a variable to ever be modified keep
in mind that this is all valid python
code it won't affect the speed of your
program and it's completely optional
even if your code has Type hints and
VSCO is warning you of an error but you
still choose to run the code python is
not going to stop you and you will still
get a runtime error type hints are just
hints clues for the type Checker python
will run your code with or without them
the hints are for us the developers as
well to write better code and to get
more help from our code editors and
better autocomplete type hints can be
added to your code incrementally you
don't have to do it all at once they are
completely optional and forever will be
as stated on the python website python
will remain a dynamically typed language
and the authors have no desire to ever
make type hint mandatory even by
convention now even though they are not
mandatory they will still increase the
quality of your code they will allow you
to read your code and understand what
it's doing faster they will help you
work with big code bases and big themes
and they will give you a better
developer experience on the text editor
of your choice to learn more about all
the type hints you can use in Python
check out the documentation of the
typing module on the official python
documentation website as well as the
mypai documentation website and don't
forget that if you want to learn to code
for free with me please click the link
below to join many of the free courses
on python JavaScript react react native
go and typescript among many others that
we have made for you with love for free
let me know in the comments what do you
think about type hint on python are you
going to use them are you using them
already write it down on the comments
I'm going to be looking at them right
now thank you for watching see you in
the next one stay free love yourself bye